That is at least my theory about the
theory of coding. It's the same as if
you had somebody doing it for you,
right? Like if you if you had a a dev
doing the work for you, if you delegated
it to somebody else, like you wouldn't
go into their work in progress code and
change one thing. You would wait until
the code review came in or you would
wait until the merge request came in or
whatever, but you would give them the
opportunity to do the thing you asked
them to do because you know that they
spent the last 4 hours building this up
in their mind. Claude does it in 20
seconds. People do it in a couple hours.
And you wouldn't want to destroy this
this integrity of their their internal
representation.
>> I love this 98%. That's how much of
Arvid Kal's code is written by AI. And
he's not just blindly accepting whatever
Claude spits out. He's built an entire
system to make sure that AI actually
understands his product. So, I invited
Arvid to join me today for the very
first installment of builder methods.
It's a new series here on the channel
where I'm bringing on fellow builders to
share their screens and show us how they
actually work in this AI first era. And
so Arvid Khal is an indie founder. You
might know him from his build and public
journey which he shares regularly over
on Twitter and on his podcast. So Arvid
created a SAS product called Podscan.
That's a podcast monitoring platform
which you can find out about at
podscan.fm.
But what really caught my attention is
how he systemized his AI development
workflow. So in this episode, you're
going to see his actual IDE setup, how
he set up his claw.md file and his
workspace. And what really impressed me
was Arvid's approach to platform
documentation where he literally
recorded video of himself walking
through his app like he's training a new
developer. And then he had Claude turn
his walkthroughs into docs. And you'll
also see us dig into this concept that
Arvid calls comprehension debt or why
you need to stay synced up with what AI
writes even when you're not writing the
code yourself. And by the way, if we
haven't met, I'm Brian Castle. I run
Builder Methods where I help
professional builders stay ahead of the
curve when it comes to building with AI.
And every Friday, I send my builder
briefing. That's a free 5-minute read to
help keep you sharp in your craft. You
can get yours by going to
buildermethods.com. Now, you'll find the
notes for today's episode linked up
below. And if you're a Builder Methods
Pro member, then you'll get access to
the full unedited recording where Arvid
and I talked for over an hour and we
heard Arvid's story of how he made the
transition from a career as a full stack
developer into this AI first builder of
successful SAS products. Why don't you
share your screen if you would and I
want to get a lay of the land of like
what your like you come in every
morning, you you get to work. What does
your screen look like? What are you
looking at? What tools are are you
opening up first? Do you see the world's
most beautiful
all text PHP storm at this point? All
right. So, you're using PHP Storm.
That's all I do. I have a browser window
with the application somewhere else. Um,
yeah, we might might share that too at
some point, but this is this is kind of
where PCan lives. It's a PHP Storm app.
This up here, this this window is me
just having code or whatever. We we
currently see my my system prompt, which
is probably one of the most interesting
things I can share. And then on the
bottom here we have um you know vite is
running and rendering the application.
There's a a kind of scheduler. There's a
queue because Laravel I I'm using um
horizon for like backend process manage
management and there's a lot of backend
process to manage which potan cuz it's
all this data flowing in and out um at
somebody else's leisure right somebody
releases a podcast [clears throat]
episode I need to deal with it. So
that's what hap what's happening here.
Then uh what is this? There is uh
another this this is actually logs like
I I have my log streaming here and then
a little little window just a couple of
tiny uh prompts where I can do stuff
like uh artisan commands or or get push
stuff like that. All right, so Arvid's
about to show us his claw.md file which
is sort of like a system prompt that
sets the stage for everything that
claude code does in his codebase. So
what's interesting to pay attention to
here is his use of the augster library
which helps him dial in his system
prompt. It's basically a structured way
to ensure that AI is executing his tasks
consistently every single time. Pattern
I I use I talk about all the time and
that's just like really being specific
about instructing your agent to reuse
this cuz that's what we always do
especially when you're building on an
existing app. You're going to be reusing
UI.
>> I have a couple things like this is my
cloud MD file. It is sizable. This is my
system prompt that has a lot of stuff in
there like code examples and and all
kinds of stuff. I was recommended to use
the Oxto system prompt. That's something
you might want to look into and maybe
even put if you can find it on GitHub
into uh the show notes here. This has
been an extremely helpful thing that
Oxar is is an AI coding assistant tool
and they have the system prompt that
they make you put into your project so
that then their tool which I don't use
can be more can can reliably use the
agentic loop whatever tool or whatever
agentic system you might use. This is
kind of a almost like a normalized CSS
but for um for agentic AI and this has
it is super important that you have uh
this this this what is it like the
golden rules and fundamental ethers of
of building code always just have
structured insightful thinking and be
proactive and autonomous execution like
this this thing is full of explaining to
the coding agent how a coding agent
should behave how to make good choices
and then it explains explains exactly
how it should take your prompt,
structure this into step-by-step
instructions, and then have a planning
workflow, how to stage the to stage the
planning, how to stage the
implementation, how to verify.
>> Oh, that's interesting. So, like I like
with with my uh agent OS framework that
that has like a lot of the uh like
putting like your your coding standards
and your own best practices and opinions
in there. But this,
>> as I understand it, does something a
little bit different. And it's sort of
instructing Claude code on how to
interpret your raw prompts. So you can
you can speak in a a a prompt and then
it's going to look to this
>> to sort of make sense of your ramblings.
>> That's right. Like it takes it takes
whatever you say and it tries to fit it
into this structure which it then
facilitates. I mean a lot of this is
just made up stuff, right? You kind of
tell this story to the agent and if the
agent believes it then it behaves like
that. Did you ever think that we would
think about stuff like that in coding?
>> That's unbelievable.
>> I'm narrative.
>> What I was going to ask you before you
showed this part is like, do you ever do
any like drafts of prompts? Like this is
something that I I'm doing a lot. If I
have a prompt that's about that that
length of what you have, which I have
all the time,
>> I'm going to probably speak it into a
plain text file or into the clawed web
app and go back and forth and refine the
prompt. And then when once it's ready
and it has all the details that I want,
then I get it into cloud code.
>> I I have a notion to-do thing here that
that has all my my to-dos and all the
to-dos that I will never get to. And
occasionally I just get it right in here
and then I edit it or add more. But if I
know it's a feature that has like like
this one here, right, that was just me
speaking for like 3 4 minutes. I know
exactly what I wanted it to do and it
was well scoped cuz it was just an admin
feature. I tend to just like speak it
right into the prompt here. Like I I
still speak I still uh dictate the
thing, but I put it right into the
prompt window and then it shows up as
this like I like I said this pasted text
one pasted text two plus eight lines,
right? That's just me. This is I think
two segments of me speaking and if it's
shorter it puts the full text in
otherwise it considers it a paste.
That's how cloud code deals with
>> but the the the system prompt is is
critical because that governs like any
approach and you will see this like um
hopefully I can scroll here but this is
how it how it checks. This is how it uh
puts actual structure in here right it
says now executing the implementation
plan phase one core job implementation
it goes to 9.1.1 create this
prioritization job and then 9.1.2 to
imple implement the custoing ID based
chunking logic and then it goes through
all of this explains to me what it's
going to do and then it does it
>> that phased breakdown is driven by your
system
>> that is the first thing in the system
prompt yeah
>> which which like sort of interpreted the
content of your raw prompt
>> yeah it it reformats it into a a
normalized standard that then um it
treats as if it's part of a normalized
behavior and implements it and has a
output that is reliable and tells you
exactly what happened when and uh you
know it has its own verification step
and then at the end it has a summary
that it tells you exactly what it did
and then obviously it forgot something
because it's decoding and then it says
you are absolutely right and then it
fixed the thing and then it worked. All
right, now here's where it gets really
clever. Arvid didn't just write
documentation for his codebase. He
recorded video of himself walking
through Podcan like he was onboarding a
new developer on his team. And then he
had Claude turn those video transcripts
into structured platform documentation.
It's like giving AI the same context
that a human teammate would get on their
first week. Watch how this plays out. I
have another document here in my let me
see my documents folder. It's called
platform docs. And this is uh the result
of me going like in a in a video that I
recorded through my whole platform and
explaining every single bit in in a
transcript and then I took the
transcript and I told Claude the web
version turn this into a markdown file
that explains every single thing about
this product. What I want it to be, who
it's for, what I said this is supposed
to do.
>> I want to dig into this. So you you
recorded a video Yeah.
>> of you walking through as if like you
have a a new developer sitting right
next to you. you're training this new
employee on your business, but you're
doing it on video. And even though like
Claude can't view your video, it can
just based on your transcript, it can
understand and and build like the
technical schema.
>> That's exactly what it was. I took great
care to explain I'm now clicking on the
alerts.
>> Oh, interesting.
>> Right. And then uh on the left side you
will find or on the top you'll find the
latest mentions and all alerts. And then
if you click on this, you see the
alerts. And then I said if you click on
each alert or any alert you can then you
know get go into the alert uh view or
whatever. And from there it figured all
of this out. And each of these sections
has a clear explanation of uh what the
window does. When you've claimed the
podcast you gain the ability to edit its
information through the edit podcast
window. And then it shows what the tabs
do and what the data in those tabs is,
what flags, what values they might have.
So I went through every single UI
component. It took me like yeah an hour
or so to go through every every one of
these and the transcript thrown into
clot with a prompt of make this cool
pretty much uh gave me this file and now
whenever I'm building something new or
I'm changing something I can say scan
the platform docs and see if this fits
where it would fit which gives it
coherence.
>> Oh this this is great. This is I mean
this is like my favorite part of the
episode. Okay this next concept is
something that I think every developer
using AI tools needs to hear. Arvin
calls it comprehension debt. So here's
the problem. When Claude writes code for
you, it builds a temporary mental model,
a theory of how things work and then
that context just disappears. AI doesn't
remember, but you or your future agents
still need to maintain that code. So if
you're not reviewing what gets written,
you're accumulating this debt which
you'll have to pay back later. So let's
see how Arvid handles this. I wrote
about this and I talked about it in my
podcast a couple weeks ago. Like there's
something called comprehension debt
which is a form of technical debt. It's
like we before cloud code, before
agentic code, uh we we we had this
theory of our codebase in our minds
otherwise it wouldn't exist. Right?
That's the the first couple months of
pods was I knew exactly what pot was in
my brain and then I kind of coded it
into reality by putting it into this
this codebase. Now that cloud code is
working for me, um it has its own theory
of what the product is and that is the
mix of the system prompt and this this
platform docs and the com the comments
and the actual code. That is not
necessarily what I have in mind and it
could well be slightly different enough
that cloud code just does things
differently and changes the overall
actual theory of the codebase that is in
my mind is kind of desynchronized at
that moment. So I do this step so I can
recynchronize my theory of the codebase
that I have in my mind with what the
actual theory of the codebase is as
expressing code. Hope this makes sense.
And if you don't do that then your
understanding of what the codebase is
drifts away from the actual codebase and
you end up with code you don't
understand. And the problem is that the
agentic coding system does not retain
the theory. like they built the theory
up like when I start this when I say
what I want and I hit enter cloud code
builds this internal theory of what the
codebase is it changes the code and then
it ends it says all changes are built
and ready and it discards the the
internal theory completely whatever it
was thinking the codebase was is
completely gone
>> yeah it has to like relearn that
>> with a person you can kind of ask them
what are you thinking here and then they
slowly rebuild it in their mind and they
go oh yeah that's what I was thinking
and then they tell you hopefully but
with cloud code it is unretrievable. It
will never come back. So I need to take
this step to rebuild this internally and
maybe adjust the comments or maybe
adjust my my prompt or whatever so that
there is like this unified theory of the
product that I have which is why I step
through each of these changes. I also
instruct and this is part of my system
prompt cloud code to write tests for
anything it does. I've never been a
tester. This is the first software
project that ever has amazing. Like I
I've I've gone through phases of being
like like over testing and then I just
got fed up with writing so many tests
and now now that we're here like I can
just have have Claude write tests for
everything.
>> Claude has like I had zero tests a
couple months ago. This um current
incarnation of hot scan has like 3,500
tests with like 12 14,000 assertions in
there.
>> And you're doing like test driven as
part of the original prompt or or doing
afterwards? I I do super delayed
test-driven development. I uh put things
into production and then 2 days later I
run the test occasionally like when I
when I know again like this is also when
I do the the git github uh co-pilot um
step through every change thing for
critical things for like really
important changes I run my tests before
I commit obviously and for for things
like this um I I could run the test now
but 10 minutes of I I don't really know
I'm touching files that I know nothing
else is touching it's fine. This is all
no side effects stuff, but usually I run
my tests before the larger things and I
instruct it to um run those tests
internally when they touch things that
already have tests,
>> right? That's that's what it does.
That's the agentic loop too. Like it
goes in and checks is there a test for
this? Okay, I'm going to run it and see
if my implementation breaks it. If so,
let me see if I need to fix it. And if
not, well, then it asks me, it stops and
says, well, what should we do? And then
I they go in. If you had to like put a
number on it, uh, in like on average,
would you say that you're like what
percentage of the work of the code are
you letting not only letting cloud code
write, but like you are not touching it
when it goes to production? like how how
much at at this at the end of this phase
as you're getting ready to push to
production or before that how much are
you going into the codebase and saying
like you know what I'm just going to
write this part myself or I'm going to
polish this up myself and write it. So
hand touch code if I were to count it as
lines per day I could probably count on
one or two hands.
>> Wow. it it is likely 98 99% of code that
I just allow it to write
>> because because even even the the small
tweaks like I I have a lot of small
tweaks that I then just ask cloud to
make for
>> that's exactly right you know
>> like oh no this should be a little bit
grayer than the other thing that's the
thing and this is either laziness or
genius or something in between I'm not
sure about it but it's like it's easier
for me to say no make it a little bit
more gray and then go back to the other
distraction that I have than to try and
get into the file like this particular
panel okay now This is this color. Okay.
Well, it's like I need to change it. I
know that the change is literally one
line. I'd rather just ask cloud to do it
>> because it sometimes has um side effects
that I'm not considering. That's the
thing with the theory. That's and that's
maybe why this this uh this
comprehension that is is a really
relevant concept for us as developers
with AI coding to understand the theory
that Claude builds internally for the
process of you running it for this
particular feature is let's say
internally complete. like Claude knows
that this color here also is referenced
somebody somewhere else like in an
overlay or in a you know in a popup that
it also has built for you. You as the
person that sees it in the front end,
you might not know. So when you say I'm
going to go in here and I change this to
a slightly different like purple or
whatever, you might miss the other
incarnation of purple. But when I say
this purple needs to be a little bit
less purple,
>> Claude internally understands with its
current temporary theory that this
purple is in four locations. I need to
change all four.
>> So it's so true. And I notic that I go
in
>> totally. And that I I notice this all
the time when when it's like I know that
the little tweak that I'm asking Claude
or cursor to make for me, I know that
it's so small. It's like one line and
then and then I do that and then it
found like three or more three or four
more instances of like little fixes that
I totally had no idea that that should
have been fixed.
>> That is at least my theory about the
theory of coding. Do not interfere
manually with the internal. It's the
same as if you had somebody doing it for
you, right? Like if you if you had a a
dev doing the work for you if you
delegated it to somebody else like you
wouldn't go into their work in progress
code and change one thing. So two things
really stood out to me from this
conversation with Arvid. First, I
noticed how much he's invested in his
system prompts and documentation. That
video to docs workflow that he showed
us, that's not something that most
builders are doing, but it's clearly
what lets him hand off real work to AI
with confidence. He's built himself a
system that gives AI a holistic
understanding of his product, and that
seems to be what makes the difference.
Second is this idea of comprehension
debt. When 98% of his code is AI
written, Arvid stays in sync with what's
being created. The AI builds a temporary
theory, does its work, and then moves
on. But he's the one maintaining that
code 6 months from now, or his future
agents are. So, he reviews what gets
written, and keeps his mental model up
to date. That's a discipline that's
worth thinking about. Now, in my full
unedited conversation with Arvid, we go
deeper into his backstory of how he
transitioned from being a full stack
developer into this AI first SAS
founder. So, if you want access to that,
consider becoming a Builder Methods Pro
member. You'll get access to all my
interviews, all my workshops, our
community of builders, and you'll access
my library of courses on building with
AI. You can join us by going to
buildermethods.com/pro.
Now, Arvid was able to successfully make
that transition from career full stack
developer to fully AI first builder. And
if you want to do the same, then you'll
need to master a few key skills, some of
which are new ones. So, I made a video
all about that here. So, right after you
hit subscribe on the channel, I'll see
you over there next. Let's keep
building.